Guide to the Lower East Side Photograph Collection 1901 PR 251
New-York Historical Society
Lower East Side photograph collection
1901
New-York Historical Society
PR 251
4.02 Linear feet (3 boxes)
Photographs show the neighborhood surrounding Delancey Street in New York City; the buildings and streets shown, many serving a Jewish immigrant population, were subsequently demolished during the construction of the Williamsburg Bridge.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John W. Judge, May 11, 1905.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Historical Note
When New York City's Williamsburg Bridge, originally called the East River Bridge, was designed, a plaza was provided at each end. It was decided that a clear space, at least 32 feet wide, was needed on each side of the bridge to protect the structure from fire, as well as to prevent accident to adjoining buildings. This design required the city to clear all existing properties from an area measuring 150 feet, along the south side of Delancey Street, from the East River, west to Clinton Street.
Construction of the bridge began on November 7, 1896. The following year, the East River Bridge Commission began to purchase the needed properties from their owners. However, after some legal issues, the commission was forced to acquire the majority of land through condemnation. An estimated 10,000 people in the Lower East Side neighborhood were displaced by the project.
Scope and Content Note
The Lower East Side Photograph Collection spans the period from March to June 1901 and contains sixty-three silver gelatin photographs of buildings, on and around Delancey Street, before they were demolished to build the Williamsburg Bridge. The photographs show the markets, shops, saloons, and other businesses in the area, signs for many of these are in Hebrew. The images also capture the residents of the neighborhood, including several children, on the street and peering from windows. This neighborhood survey provides a unique view of life in this predominately Jewish neighborhood.
N. L. Coe, a photographer with a studio located at 681 Broadway, took all but two photographs in the collection. The remaining two images are marked "A. J. Drummond." They are all mounted on board and hand labeled, with the addresses written on the board, and sometimes directly on the image itself. While they may have been commissioned by the city, or made for personal use, it is not known why these photographs were taken.
Arrangement
Photographs are first alphabetized by street and then arranged by address.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Other images of Delancey Street can be found in the Geographic File (PR 020) and the Subway Construction Photograph Collection (PR 069).
On-line Access to Digital Copies
The photographs in the collection are all available on-line via the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library
Gelatin silver prints.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Jews -- New York (State) -- New York.; Poor -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York.; Tenement houses -- New York (State) -- New York.; Working classes -- Dwellings.; Coe, N. L., (photographer)
- On-line access to images (Digital-file On-line)
- Attorney Street, 63-71 & 64-68, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- Cannon Street, 35-43 & 44-46, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Clinton Street, 112-118, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Columbia Street, 36-46 & 35-43, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Delancey Street, 169-199, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Delancey Street, 201-209, [1901] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Delancey Street, 219-223, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
- Delancey Street, 233-239 & 241-243, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
- Delancey Street, 251-259, 269-281 & 293-299, 1901 Mar-Apr (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
- Delancey Street, 305-323, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
- Goerck Street, 36-38 & 37-49, 1901 Mar-Jun (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
- Lewis Street, 35-39 & 36-38, 1901 Mar-Jun (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
- Lewis Street, 41 & 38-42, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
- Mangin Street, 30 & 35-41, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
- Pitt Street, 31-41 & 38-44, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15)
- Ridge Street, 55-63 & 56-64, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 3, Folder 16)
- Sheriff Street, 35-39 & 38-44, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
- Tompkins Street, 21, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
- Willett Street, 34-38 & 35-43, 1901 Mar (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)